Guide to the Yamato Ichihashi Papers SC0071 SC0071
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- War Relocation
  - War Relocation, 1943, January -June (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - T.L.S. Payson Treat to Ichihashi, Apr 27, 1943
    - T.L.S. Edgar E. Robinson to Ichihashi, Apr 28, 1943
    - A.L.S. Lynn [White], to Ichihashi, Apr 29, 1943
    - Repatriation applicants, May 1,1943
    - Cultural problems of the Japanese in America, May 1, 1943
    - T.L. Ichihashi to Payson [Treat] re: conditions of Tule Lake., May 4,1943
    - T.L. Ichihashi to Edgar [Robinson], May 5, 1943
    - T.L.S. Payson Treat to Ichihashi, May 9,1943
    - A.L.S. K. Kawakami to Ichihashi, May 19,1943
    - Relocation of Japanese Americans, WRA, May 1943
    - T.L.S. Payson Treat to Ichihashi, Jun 2, 1943
    - WRA Administrative Instruction: Community Evacuee Government, June 5,1943
    - Report on Evacuee resistances to relocation, Jun 8, 1943
    - Memorandum re: Spanish Consul's inquiry into the threat of Japanese in U.S., June 18,1943
    - "An Appeal to All Americans of Japanese Ancestry and their Parents", Jun 23, 1943
    - T.L.S. Payson Treat to Ichihashi, Jun 24, 1943
    - WRA memo - re: Employment quota, Jun 30, 1943
    - Hospital Koenkai, June Report, 1943
  - War Relocation, 1943, July -December (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - WRA memos
    - List of possible Japanese repatriates, Jul 8, 1943
    - "Chronology - Segregation", July 12,1943
    - T.L. Ichihashi to Payson [Treat] re: conditions at Tule Lake, July 8,1943, July 24,1943
    - T.L.S. Payson Treat to Ichihashi, July 29,1943
    - WRA Application for Leave Clearance, July 31,1943
    - Hospital Koenkai, July report, 1943
    - 2 telegrams from Woodrow Ichihashi, Aug 4, Aug 11, 1943
    - T.L. Ichihashi to Payson [Treat] re: WRA policy of segregation, Aug 11, 1943
    - T.L.S. Payson Treat to Ichihashi, re: trip from Tule Lake, Aug 19, 1943
    - Japanese government message, expression of sympathy, Aug 20, 1943
    - A.L.S. Frank Matsumoto to Ichihashi, re: trip from Tule Lake, Aug 20, 1943
    - T.L.S. Edward L. Tatum to Ichihashi, re: rental of Ichihashi home., Aug 20, 1943
    - Postcard, Frank Matsumoto to Ichihashi, Aug 21, 1943
    - WRA memo, formation of an official community representatives committee, Aug 24, 1943
    - "Segregation of Persons of Japanese Ancestry in Tule Lake Relocation Center," WRA, August, 1943
    - "Things to do and remember in preparing for your train trip", Aug 26, 1943
    - A.L.S. Ichihashi to Payson [Treat]
    - T.L. Ichihashi to "Ito Kun" re: trip to Amache, Colorado., Oct 25, 1943
    - T.L. Ichihashi to Payson [Treat] re: trip to Amache, Oct 31, 1943
    - T.L. Ichihashi to Dr. Opler, Nov 1, 1943
    - "Creative Evacuee Committee to aid resettlement", Nov 13, 1943
    - Memo, Granada project, Amache, Colorado, re: proposals for special counseling, Nov 19, 1943
    - Copies of newspaper clippings re: Japanese Americans
    - List of members of Relocation Advisory Board.
    - T.L. Ichihashi to Payson [Treat], re: Japanese Relations with Korea and China, Dec 28, 1943
    - Calendar of Events, 1942,1943
    - WRA Minidoka Project, information.
  - War Relocation, Miscellaneous and undated material, 1943- (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Poem - "at Tulelake Project"
    - Report on the Segregation with Special Reference to the work of the Community Representatives (Jikyaku-IIN) to date
    - "Problems of Cultural Assimilation"
    - Suggestions for conduct of Segregation Interviews
    - T.L. Ichihashi to Hon. Edward J. Ennis, Department of Justice, re: release from status of parolee
    - "Welcome Tuleans!" informative booklet published at Amache, Colorado
    - Key Reporter (Phi Beta Kappa), Autumn, 1943
    - "Our 110,000 New Boarders"
    - Schedual (sic] of train trips
    - Administrative instruction #78: storage and transportation of household goods, etc.
    - WRA: request for transportation of property and power of attorney
    - IKE NO BO - Flower Arrangements
    - "Outcasts" by Caleb Foot
    - "These are Our Parents" by George Morimitsu
    - Congressional record proceeding re: Pearl Harbor
    - WRA Administrative Instruction: Repatriation and Exchange
    - "Steel Facts"
    - "Ships
  - War Relocation, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Questionnaire, survey and results of questions asked of Japanese-Americans at Amache.
  - Daily Tulean Dispatch, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - War Relocation - Ichihashi - History of Tule Lake Relocation Center - Handwritten copy (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Reports and Diary, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Description of the relocation center
    - Are the Japanese ancestry here loyal to the U.S.?
    - Loyality of the Nisei by Frank Hijikata
    - The Social Background of Nisei prior to evacuation
    - A Nisei Diary
  - War Relocation - The Tule Lake Interlude, May 27, 1942-1943, introduction by Yamato Ichihashi (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - War Relocation, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - T.L.S. Payson Treat to Ichihashi, Jan 4, 1944
    - T.L.S. Kenji Ito (?) to Ichihashi, re: conditions at Minidoka Project, Hunt, Idaho., Jan 7, 1944
    - Minidoka Irrigator, Nov 8, 1944
    - T.L.S. Kenji Ito to Dr. and Mrs. Ichihashi, re: conditions at Minidoka, Jan 11, 1944
    - T.L. Ichihashi to "Shirai Kun," re: conditions at Amache, Jan 15, 1944
    - "Americans facing a problem", Jan 16, 1944
    - T.L. Ichihashi to "Ito Kun" re: conditions at Amache, Jan 16, 1944
    - T.L. Ichihashi to Payson [Treat] re: History of relations between Japan and Korea, Jan 19, 1944
    - T.L.S. Kenji Ito to Ichihashi re: report on labor relations at Minidoka Project, Jan 19, 1944
    - T.L. to Edward H. Spicer from John Rademaker, re: reinstitution of the draft for Nisei, Feb 16, 1944, Feb 22, 1944
    - Amache Consumer Enterprises, Inc., income and expense statement, March 1-31, 1944
    - T.L. Ichihashi to Dillon S. Myer, re: short history of WRA, Mar 14, 1944
    - Minutes of the Special Joint Committee for giving information to draft-age nisei, Mar 17, 1944
    - Information on Granada Project, Amache, Colorado
    - T.L re: Rohwer Co-operative Enterprises, Inc., May 31,1944 to June 15,1944
    - Granada Project Memorandum, Community Analysts trip to California and back., July 10,1944
    - WRA Administrative notice, re: adult education., July 17,1944
    - Factors and Attitudes in Resettlement Problem
    - T.L. Ichihashi to Payson [Treat] re: conditions at Amache, Sep 22, 1944
    - Personal questions of the undersigned (George Sakiyawa), Sep 23, 1944
    - WRA - Relocation outlood
    - T.L. Ichihashi to Payson [Treat] re: conditions at Amache, Nov 5, 1944
    - T.L. Ichihashi to Payson [Treat] re: conditions at Amache, Nov 26, 1944
    - T.L. Ichihashi to Payson [Treat] re: possibility of evacuees returning home., Dec 19, 1944
  - War Relocation, 1944- (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous and undated papers.
    - The problem of re-settlement
    - The Nature of Residual Population in the Center, Summer 1944
    - Some papers in Japanese
  - War Relocation, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous reports and studies
    - Studies on population and re-location
    - Re-settlement after the removal of exclusion order
  - Amache Community Council Minutes, 1944 Oct-Dec (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - War Relocation, 1944- (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Adult Education program reports, surveys, list of participants
  - War Relocation, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - T.L. Ichihashi to "Ito Kun", re: problem involved with evacuees returning home, Jan 15, 1945
    - WRA, memorandum, Jan 29, 1945
    - A Summary of problems and questions submitted by center residents, Feb 10, 1945
    - Reports on Reactions of Center Residents on newly announced policy of the center closure.
    - Amache Community Council Minutes, Feb 27, Mar 1, Mar 13, Mar 6, 1945
    - Telegram - P.J. Treat to Ichihashi, re: Ichihashi trip back to Palo Alto, Apr 24, 1945
    - A.L. Ichihashi to "Kawashiri San" re: trip back to Palo Alto, May 30 ,1945
    - T.L.S. Stanford University, Assistant Business Manager to Ichihashi, re: rental of campus housing, June 9 ,1945
    - T.L. Ichihashi to McFarling, re: requirements of parolees after their re-settlement, June 25, 1945
    - T.L. Ichihashi to "Kiyowaza Danzo" re: trip from Amache, June 27 ,1945
    - T.L.S. Sakae Kawashiri to Ichihashi re: Yakohoma Specie Bank of San Francisco
    - T.L.S. James G. Lindley, Granada Project director to Ichihashi, July 23, 1945
    - T. L, S. "Delmer" to Ichihashi, Aug 1, 1945
    - T.L. Ichihashi to "Kawashiri San", 3-Aug-45
    - T.L.S. Sakae Kawashiri to Ichihashi, re: relocation plans, Aug 6, 1945
    - T L. Ichihashi to "Sto Kun,", Aug 19, 1945
    - A.L.S. S. Kawashiri to Ichihashi, re: relocation plans., Aug 30, 1945
    - T.L. Ichihashi to "Kawashiri Kun," re: relocation conditions, Sep 4, 1945
    - T.L.S. Alice Westbrook to Ichihashi, Sep 6, 1945
    - T.L.S. S. Kawashiri to Ichihashi, Sep 11, 1945
    - T.L.S. H. Hamatani to Dr. and Mrs. Ichihashi, re: resettlement in Sacramento, Sep 12, 1945
    - T.L. S. "Delmer" to Ichihashi, re: plans for future, Sep 17, 1945
    - T.L.S. Alice Westbrook to Ichihashi, re: bills to be paid., Sep 18, 1945
    - A.L.S. Sakae Kawkishiri to Ichihashi, re: settlement in Berkeley, Sep 19, 1945
    - T.L.S. Kenji Ito to Ichihashi, re: resettlement problems, Sep 19, 1945
    - T.L. Mrs. Ichihashi to State Banking Department, re: claim against Yokohama Specie bank., Sep 24, 1945
    - T. L. Ichihashi to "Ito Kun,", Sep 24, 1945
    - T.L.S. Ichihashi requesting return of telephone service to his home, Sep 28, 1945
    - A.L.S. S. Kawashiri to Ichihashi, re: working as a gardener in Berkeley, Sep 29, 1945
    - T.L.S. Kenji Ito to Ichihashi, re: plans for resettling family, Oct 4, 1945
    - T.L. Ichihashi to "Ito Kun,", Oct 7, 1945
    - A.L.S. "Delmer" to Ichihashi, re: trip from Honolulu to Washington, D.C., Nov 4, 1945
    - T.L.S. denial to Ichihashi to have telephone installed in his home, Nov 9, 1945
    - T.L. Ichihashi to "Ito Kun,", Nov 1, 1945, Dec 10, 1945
    - Various undated papers, some in Japanese
  - War Relocation and Resettlement, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - T.L.S. Kenneth Yasuda to Ichihashi, re: Japanese copyrights, Jan 2, 1946
    - A.L.S. "Delmer" to Ichihashi, 3-Jan-46
    - T.L.S. Immigration and Naturalization Service to Ichihashi, re: possible repatriation to Japan, Jan 14, 1946
    - A.L. Ichihashi to Professor Trotter, re: internment experiences
    - A.L. Ichihashi to Delmer Brown, Jan 6, 1946
    - T.L.S. Kenji Ito to Ichihashi, Jan 19, 1946
    - T.L. Ichihashi to "Ito Kun", Jan 22, 1946
    - A.L.S. Hamatani to Dr. and Mrs. Ichihashi re: problems faced by resettling Japanese, Feb 1, 1946
    - T.L.S. Kenji Ito to Ichihashi, re: post war conditions, Feb 10, 1946
    - A.L.S. S.V. Christianson to Ichihashi, re: snapshot taken of Ichihashi's sister, Feb 18, 1946
    - T.L.S. Stanford Committee on Public Exercises to Ichihashi, re: participation in Founder's Day, Feb 25, 1946
    - T.L. Ichihashi to Shizuko (sister), Feb 21, 1946
    - T.L.S. Hamatani to Ichihashi, re: Civil Rights Defense Union, Mar 3, 1946
    - A.L.S. Delmer [Brown] to Ichihashi, Mar 5, Mar 11, 1946
    - T.L.S. Payson [Treat] to Ichihashi, Mar 19, 1946
    - T.L.S. Kenji Ito to Ichihashi, Apr 9, 1946
    - T.L.S. Delmer [Brown] to Ichihashi, re: research, Apr 20, 1946
    - A.L.S. Ichihashi to his sister, n.d. general greetings, Apr 24, 1946
    - T.L.S. Talbot Bielefeldt to Ichihashi, re: delivering Ichihashi's letter to his sister, Apr 28, 1946
    - T.L.S. Delmer [Brown] to Ichihashi, re: research, May 5,1946
    - T.L.S. Bielefeldt to Ichihashi, re: future plans uncertain, May 7,1946
    - T.L.S. Kenji Ito to Ichihashi, re: housing problems, May 14,1946
    - T.L. Ichihashi to St. Colonel [Bielefeldt], re: sending packages to Japan, May 21,1946
    - T.L.S. Bielefeldt to Ichihashi, re: uncertain plans on going to Japan, May 26, 1946
    - T.L.S. Kenji Ito to Ichihashi, re: alien land law, June 24, 1946
    - T.L.S. "Geo" to Ichihashi, re: stay in Japan, Sep 5, 1946
    - A.L.S. Shizuko to her brother Ichihashi, Sep 12, 1946
  - War Relocation's aftermath - Damage claim (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence and forms, 1951-52
  - War Relocation - miscellaneous newspaper clippings, 1942 ,1945 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - War Relocation - Tule Lake, 1942- (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Minutes of Council Meetings:
      - June 16,1942
      - June 23,1942
      - June 30,1942
      - July 7,1942
      - July 14,1942
      - July 21,1942
      - July 28,1942
      - Aug 5, 1942
      - Aug 11, 1942
      - Aug 18, 1942
      - Aug 25, 1942
      - Sep l, 1942
      - Sep 5, 1942
      - Sep 7, 1942
      - Sep 13, 1942
      - Sep 15, 1942
      - Sep 22, 1942
    - Report to Councilmen, Aug 29, 1942
    - Memo: Election of Fair Practice Committee Members, Sep 15, 1942
    - Charter of the Tule Lake Relocation Project in Japanese
    - Charter of Tule Lake Planning Board
  - War Relocation, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - WRA office memorandum re: registration and registration notices, Feb 13, 1943
    - Daily Tulean Dispatch, Feb 17, 1943
    - Registration forms filled out by Ichihashi family
    - Statement of U.S. Citizen of Japanese Ancestry filled out by Woodrow Wilson Ichihashi
    - Application for leave clearance filled out by Woodrow W. Ichihashi
    - Special Council Meeting minutes, Feb 12, 1943
- Diaries
  - Diaries, 1943-1946 (Box 9)
  - Diaries, 1947-1951 (Box 10)
  - Diaries, 1952-1957 (Box 11)
  - Diaries, 1958-1963 (Box 12)